Wild CHAPTER 1 The studio was filled with the rich odor of roses, and when the light summer
wind stirred amidst the trees of the garden, there came through the open door
the heavy scent of the lilac, or the more delicate perfume of the pink flowering
thorn. From the corner of the divan of Persian saddle bags on which he was
lying, smoking, as was his custom, innumerable cigarettes, Lord Henry Waton could just
catch the gleam of the honey sweet and honey colored blossoms of a laburnum,
whose tremulous branches seemed hardly able to bear the burden of a beauty so
Flamel likee as theirs; and now and then the fantastic shadows of birds in flight
flitted across the long tuser silk curtain that were stretched in front of
the huge window, producing a kind of momentary Japanese effect, and making him
think of those palid Jade faced painters of Tokyo who, through the medium of an
art that is necessarily immobile, seek to convey the sense of swiftness and motion.
The sullen murmur of the bees shouldering their way through the long
unmown grass, or circling with monotonous insistence around the dusty guilt horns
of the straggling woodbine, seemed to make the stillness more
oppressive. The dim roar of London was like the bordon note of a distant
organ. In the center of the room, clamped to an upright easel, stood the fulllength
portrait of a young man of extraordinary personal beauty, and in front of it, some
little distance away, was sitting the artist himself, Basil hallwood whose
sudden disappearance some years ago caused, at the time, such public
excitement and gave rise to so many strange conjectures. As the painter looked at the
gracious and comely form he had so skillfully mirrored in his art, a smile
of pleasure passed across his face, and seemed about to linger there. But he
suddenly started up, and closing his eyes, placed his fingers upon the lids, as
though he sought to imprison within his brain some curious dream from which he feared he might
awake. “It is your best work, Basil, the best thing you have ever done,” said Lord
Henry languidly. “You must certainly send it next year to the grovner The Academy
is too large and too vulgar. Whenever I have gone there, there
have been either so many people that I have not been able to see the pictures,
which was dreadful, or so many pictures that I have not been able to see the
people, which was worse. The groer is really the only place.”
“I don’t think I shall send it anywhere,” he answered, tossing his head back in
that odd way that used to make his friends laugh at him at Oxford. “No, I
won’t send it anywhere.” Lord Henry elevated his eyebrows and looked at him in amazement
through the thin blue wreaths of smoke that curled up in such fanciful whirls
from his heavy opium tainted cigarette.
“Not send it anywhere? My dear fellow, why?
Have you any reason? What odd chaps you painters are you You do anything in the
world to gain a reputation. As soon as you have one, you seem to want to throw
it away. It is silly of you, for there is only one thing in the world worse than
being talked about, and that is not being talked about. A portrait like this would
set you far above all the young men in England, and make the old men quite
jealous, if old men are ever capable of any emotion.” “I know you will laugh at me,”
he replied, “but I really can’t exhibit it.
I have put too much of myself into it.” Lord Henry stretched himself out on the
divan and laughed. “Yes, I knew you would; but it is quite true, all the
same.” “Too much of yourself in it! Upon my word Basel I didn’t know you were so
vain; and I really can’t see any resemblance between you, with your rugged
strong face and your cold black hair, and this young Adonis, who looks as if he was
made out of ivory and rose leaves Why, my dear Basil, he is a narcissist and you—
—well, of course you have an intellectual expression and all that. But beauty, real
beauty, ends where an intellectual expression begins. Intellect is in itself
a mode of exaggeration, and destroys the harmony of any face. The moment one sits
down to think, one becomes all nose, or all forehead, or something horrid. Look at
the successful men in any of the learned professions. How perfectly hideous they
are! Except, of course, in the Church. But then in the Church they don’t think. A
bishop keeps on saying at the age of 80
what he was told to say when he was a boy of 18 and as a natural consequence
he always looks absolutely delightful. Your mysterious young friend,
whose name you have never told me, but whose picture really fascinates me, never
thinks. I feel quite sure of that. He is some brainless beautiful creature who
should be always here in winter when we have have no flowers to look at, and
always here in summer when we want something to chill our intelligence.
Don’t flatter yourself, Basil: you are not in the least like
him.” “You don’t understand me, Harry,” answered the artist. “Of course I am not
like him. I know that perfectly well.
Indeed, I should be sorry to look like him. You shrug your shoulders I'm telling you the truth.
There is a fatality about all physical and intellectual distinction,
the sort of fatality that seems to dog through history the faltering steps of
kings. It is better not to be different from one’s fellows. The ugly and the
stupid have the best of it in this world.
They can sit at their ease and gape at the play. If they know nothing of victory,
they are at least spared the knowledge of defeat. They live as we all should
live— —undisturbed, indifferent, and without disqui They neither bring ruin upon
others, nor ever receive it from alien hands. Your rank and wealth, Harry; my
brains, such as they are— —my art, whatever it may be worth; Dorian Gray’s good looks—
—we shall all suffer for what the gods have given us, suffer
terribly.” “Dorian Gray? Is that his name?” asked Lord Henry, walking across the
studio towards Basil hallwood Yes, that is his name. I didn’t
intend to tell it to you.” “But why not?” “Oh, I can’t explain. When I like people
immensely, I never tell their names to anyone It is like surrendering a part of
them. I have grown to love secrecy. It seems to be the one thing that can make
modern life mysterious or marvelous to us. The commonest thing is delightful if one only hides
it. When I leave town now I never tell my
people where I'm going. If I did, I would lose all my pleasure. It is a silly habit,
I dare say, but somehow it seems to bring a great deal of romance into one’s life.
I suppose you think me awfully foolish about it?” “Not at all,” answered Lord Henry, “not at
all, my dear Basil. You seem to forget that I am married, and the one charm of
marriage is that it makes a life of deception absolutely necessary for both
parties. I never know where my wife is, and my wife never knows what I'm
doing. When we meet— —we do meet occasionally, when we dine out together,
or go down to the Dukes we tell each other the most absurd stories with the most serious
faces. My wife is very good at it— —much better, in fact, than I am. She never gets
confused over her dates, and I always do.
But when she does find me out, she makes no row at all. I sometimes wish she would;
but she merely laughs at me.” “I hate the way you talk about your
married life, Harry,” said Basil hallwood strolling towards the door that led into the garden.
“I believe that you are really a very good husband, but that you are thoroughly
ashamed of your own virtues. You are an extraordinary fellow.
You never say a moral thing, and you never do a wrong thing. Your cynicism is simply a
pose.” “Being natural is simply a pose, and the most irritating pose I know,” cried
Lord Henry, laughing; and the two young men went out into the garden together
and Encon themselves on a long bamboo seat that stood in the shade of a tall
laurel bush. The sunlight slipped over the polished leaves. In the grass, white
daisies were tremulous. After a pause, Lord Henry pulled out his
watch I'm afraid I must be going, Basil,” he murmured, “and before I go, I insist on
your answering a question I put to you some time ago.” “What is that?” said the painter,
keeping his eyes fixed on the ground. “You know quite well.” “I do not,
Harry.” “Well, I will tell you what it is. I want you to explain to me why you
won’t exhibit Dorian Gray’s picture. I want the real
reason.” “I told you the real reason.” “No, you did not. You said it was because there
was too much of yourself in it. Now, that is childish.” “Harry,” said Basil hallwood
looking him straight in the face, “every portrait that is painted with feeling is
a portrait of the artist, not of the sitter. The sitter is merely the accident, the
occasion. It is not he who is revealed by the painter; it is rather the painter who,
on the colored canvas, reveals himself. The reason I will not exhibit
this picture is that I am afraid that I have shown in it the secret of my own
soul.” Lord Henry laughed. “And what is that?” he asked. “I will tell you,” said holwood
but an expression of perplexity came over his face. “I am all expect ation Basil,”
continued his companion, glancing at him. “Oh, there is really very little to
tell, Harry,” answered the painter; “and I'm afraid you will hardly understand it.
Perhaps you will hardly believe it.” Lord Henry smiled, and leaning down, plucked a
pink petal daisy from the grass and examined it. “I am quite sure I shall
understand it,” he replied, gazing intently at the little golden white feathered
disc and as for believing things, I can believe anything, provided that it is quite
incredible.” The wind shook some blossoms from the trees, and the heavy lilac
blooms with their clustering stars, moved to and fro in the languid air. A
grasshopper began to cherup by the wall, and like a blue thread a long thin
dragonfly floated past on its brown gors wings. Lord Henry felt as if he could
hear Basil hallwoods heart beating, and wondered what was coming.
“The story is simply this,” said the painter after some time. “Two months ago I
went to a crush at Lady Brandon’s. You know we poor artists have to show
ourselves in society from time to time, just to remind the public that we are not
savages. With an evening coat and a white tie, as you told me once, anybody, even a
stock broker can gain a reputation for being civilized. Well, after I'd been in
the room about 10 minutes, talking to huge overdressed dowagers and tedious
academicians, I suddenly became conscious that someone was looking at me. I turned
halfway around and saw Dorian Gray for the first time. When our eyes met, I felt
that I was growing pale. A curious sensation of terror came over me. I knew
that I had come face to face with someone whose mere personality was so
fascinating that, if I allowed it to do so, it would absorb my whole nature, my
whole soul, my very art itself.
I did not want any external influence in my life. You know yourself, Harry, how
independent I am by nature. I always been my own master; had at least always been
so, till I met Dorian Gray. Then— —but I don’t know how to explain it to you.
Something seemed to tell me that I was on the verge of a terrible crisis in my
life. I had a strange feeling that fate had in store for me exquisite joys and
exquisite sorrows.
I grew afraid and turned to quit the room. It was not conscience that made me
do so: it was a sort of cowardice. I take no credit to myself for trying to
escape.” “Conscience and cowardice are really the same things Basel Conscience
is the trade name of the firm. That is all.” “I don’t believe that, Harry, and I
don’t believe you do either. However, whatever was my motive— —and it may have
been ride for I used to be very proud— —I certainly struggled to the door. There, of
course, I stumbled against Lady Brandon.
‘You are not going to run away so soon, Mr hallwood she screamed out. You know her
curiously shrill voice?” “Yes; she is a peacock in everything
but beauty,” said Lord Henry, pulling the daisy to bits with his long nervous
fingers. “I could not get rid of her. She brought me up to royalties, and people
with stars and garters, and elderly ladies with gigantic tiaras and parrot
noses. She spoke of me as her dearest friend I'd only met her once before, but
she took it into her head to lionize me.
I believe some picture of mine had made a great success at the time, at least had
been chatted about in the penny newspapers, which is the 19th century standard of
immortality. Suddenly I found myself face to face with the young man whose
personality had so stranged ly stirred me. We were quite close, almost touching.
Our eyes met again. It was reckless of me, but I asked Lady Brandon to introduce me
to him. Perhaps it was not so reckless, after all. It was simply inevitable. We
would have spoken to each other without any introduction I'm sure of that. Dorian
told me so afterwards. He, too, felt that we were destined to know each
other.” “And how did Lady and describ this wonderful young man?” asked his
companion. “I know she goes in for giving a rapid presses of all her guests. I
remember her bringing me up to a truculent and red-faced old gentleman
covered all over with orders and ribbons, and hissing into my ear, in a tragic
whisper which must have been perfectly audible to everybody in the room, the
most astounding details. I simply fled. I like to find out people for myself. But
Lady Brandon treats her guests exactly as an auctioner treats his goods. She
either explains them entirely away, or tells one everything about them except what one wants to
know.” “Poor Lady Brandon! You are hard on her, Harry!” said hallwood
listlessly. “My dear fellow, she tried to found a salon and only succeeded in
opening a restaurant. How could I admire her? But tell me, what did she say about Mr. Dorian
Gray?” “Oh, something like, ‘Charming boy— —poor dear mother and and I absolutely
inseparable. Quite forget what he does— —afraid he— —doesn’t do anything— —oh, yes,
plays the piano— —or is it the violin, dear Mr. Gray?’ Neither of us could help
laughing, and we became friends at once.” “Laughter is not at all a bad
beginning for a friendship, and it is far the best ending for one,” said the young
lord, plucking another daisy hallwood shook his head. “You don’t understand what
friendship is, Harry,” he murmured what enmity is, for that matter. You like
everyone that is to say, you are indifferent to everyone How horribly unjust of you!”
cried Lord Henry, tilting his hat back and looking up at the little clouds that,
like raveled skaines of glossy white silk, were drifting across the hollowed
turquoise of the summer sky. “Yes; horribly unjust of you. I make a
great difference between people. I choose choose my friends for their good looks,
my acquaintances for their good characters, and my enemies for their good
intellects. A man cannot be too careful in the choice of his enemies. I have not
got one who is a fool. They are all men of some intellectual power, and
consequently they all appreciate me. Is that very vain of me? I think it is rather
vain.” “I should think it was, Harry. But according to your category I must be
merely an acquaintance.” “My dear old Basil, you are much more than an
acquaintance.” “And much less than a friend.
A sort of brother, I suppose?” “Oh, brothers!
I don’t care for brothers. My elder brother won’t die, and my younger
brothers seem never to do anything else.” “Harry!” exclaimed hallwood frowning.
“My dear fellow I'm not quite serious. But I can’t help detesting my
relations. I suppose it comes from the fact that none of us can stand other
people having the same fault as ourselves. I quite sympathize with the
rage of the English democracy against what they call the vices of the upper
orders. The masses feel that drunkenness, stupidity, and immorality should be their
own special property, and that if any one of us makes an ass of himself he's
poaching on their preserves. When poor suuk got into the divorce court, their
indignation was quite magnificent. And yet I don’t suppose that 10% of the proletariat live
correctly.” “I don’t agree with a single word that you have said, and, what is more,
Harry, I feel sure you don’t either.” Lord Henry stroked his pointed
brown beard and tapped the toe of his patent leather boot with a tassled ebony
cane. “How English you are Basil! That is the second time you have made that
observation. If one puts forward an idea to a true Englishman— —always a rash thing
to do— —he never dreams of considering whether the idea is right or
wrong. The only thing he considers of any importance is whether one believes it
oneself. Now, the value of an idea has nothing whatsoever to do with the
sincerity of the man who expresses it.
Indeed, the probabilities are that the more insincere the man is, the more
purely intellectual will the idea be, as in that case it will not be colored by
either his wants, his desires, or his prejudices. However, I don’t propose to
discuss politics, sociology, or metaphysics with you. I like persons
better than principles, and I like persons with no principles better than
anything else in the world. Tell me more about Mr. Dorian Gray. How often do you see
him?” “Every day. I couldn’t be happy if I didn’t see him every day he's absolutely
necessary to me.” “How extraordinary! I thought you would never care for anything but your
art.” “He is all my art to me now,” said the painter gravely. “I sometimes think, Harry,
that there are only two eras of any importance in the world’s history. The
first is the appearance of a new medium for art, and the second is the appearance
of a new personality for art also. What the invention of oil painting was to the
Venetians, the face of Antinous was to late Greek sculpture, and the face of
Dorian Gray will someday be to me. It is not merely that I paint from him, draw
from him, sketch from him. Of course I've done all that.
But he is much more to me than a model
or a sitter. I won’t tell you that I am dissatisfied with what I have done of
him, or that his beauty is such that art cannot express it. There is nothing that
art cannot express, and I know that the work I have done, since I met Dorian Gray,
is good work, is the best work of my life.
But in some curious way— —I wonder will you understand
me?— ?—his personality has suggested to me an entire new manner in art, an entirely
new mode of style. I see things differently, I think of them differently.
I can now recreate life in a way that was hidden from me
before. ‘A dream of form in days of thought’— ’—who is it who says that? I forget;
but it is what Dorian Gray has been to me. The merely visible presence of this
lad— —for he seems to me little more than a lad, though he is really over 20 his
merely visible presence— —ah! I wonder can you realize all that that means?
Unconsciously he defines for me the lines of a fresh school, a school that is
to have in it all the passion of the romantic spirit, all the perfection of
the spirit that is Greek. The harmony of soul and body— —how much that is! We in our
madness have separated the two, and have invented a realism that is vulgar, an ideality that is
void. Harry! if you only knew what Dorian Gray is to me! You remember that landscape of mine,
for which agnu offered me such a huge price but which I would not part with? It
is one of the best things I've ever done.
And why is it so? Because, while I was painting it, Dorian Gray sat beside me.
Some subtle influence passed from him to me, and for the first time in my life I
saw in the plain woodland the wonder I had always looked for and always
missed.” “Basil, this is extraordinary! I must see Dorian Gray holwood got up from
the seat and walked up and down the garden. After some time he came back.
“Harry,” he said, “Dorian Gray is to me simply a motive in art. You might see
nothing in him. I see everything in him.
He is never more present in my work than
when no image of him is there. He is a
suggestion, as I have said, of a new man manner. I find him in the curves of
certain lines, in the loveliness and subtleties of certain colors That is
all.” “Then why won’t you exhibit his portrait?” asked Lord
Henry. “Because, without intending it, I have put into it some expression of all
this curious artistic idolatry, of which, of course I've never cared to speak to
him. He knows nothing about it. He shall never know anything about it. But the
world might guess it, and I will not bear my soul to their
shallow prying eyes. My heart shall never be put under their
microscope. There is too much of myself in the thing, Harry— —too much of myself!”
“Poets are not so scrupulous as you are.
They know how useful passion is for publication. Nowadays a broken heart will run to many
additions I hate them for it,” cried hallwood An artist should create
beautiful things, but should put nothing of his own life into them.
We live in an age when men treat art as
if it were meant to be a form of autobiography. We have lost the abstract
sense of beauty someday I will show the world what it is; and for that reason the
world shall never see my portrait of Dorian Gray.” “I think you wrong, Basil, but I won’t
argue with you. It is only the intellectually lost who ever
argue. Tell me, is Dorian Gray very fond of you?” The painter considered for a a few
moments. “He likes me,” he answered after a pause; “I know he likes me. Of course I
flatter him dreadfully. I find a strange pleasure in saying things to him that I know I shall
be sorry for having said. As a rule he's charming to me, and we sit in the studio
and talk of a thousand things. Now and then, however, he is horribly thoughtless,
and seems to take a real delight in giving me
pain. Then I feel, Harry, that I have given away my whole soul to someone who treats
it as if it were a flower to put in his
coat, a bit of decoration to charm his vanity, an ornament for a summer’s
day.” “Days in summer, Basil, are apt to linger,” murmured Lord
Henry. “Perhaps you will tire sooner than he will. It is a sad thing to think of,
but there is no doubt that genius lasts longer than beauty. That accounts for the fact that
we all take such pains to over educate ourselves.
In the wild struggle for existence, we want to have something that endures, and
so we fill our minds with rubbish and facts, in the silly hope of keeping our
place. The thoroughly well-informed man— —that is the modern ideal. And the mind of
the thoroughly well-informed man is a dreadful thing. It is like a Bricker Bra
shop, all monsters and dust, with everything priced above its proper value.
I think you will tire first, all the same someday you will look at your friend, and
he will seem to you to be a little out
of drawing, or you won’t like his tone of color or something. You will bitterly
reproach him in your own heart, and seriously think that he has behaved very badly to
you. The next time he calls, you will be perfectly cold and
indifferent. It will be a great pity, for it will alter you. What you have told me
is quite a romance, a romance of art one might call
it, and the worst of having a romance of any kind is that it leaves one so
unromantic.” “Harry, don’t talk like that. As long as I live, the personality of Dorian
Gray will dominate me. You can’t feel what I feel. You change too
often.” “Ah, my dear Basil, that is exactly why I can feel it. Those who are faithful
know only the trivial side of love: it is the faithless who know love’s
tragedies.” And Lord Henry struck a light on a dainty silver case and began to
smoke a cigarette with a self-conscious and satisfied air, as if he had summed up
the world in a phrase. There was a rustle of chering sparrows in the green lacquer leaves of
the ivy, and the blue cloud Shadows chased themselves across the grass like
swallows. How pleasant it was in the garden! And how delightful other people’s
emotions were!— !—much more delightful than their ideas, it seemed to him. One’s own
soul, and the passions of one’s friends— —those were the fascinating things in
life. He pictured to himself with silent amusement the tedious luncheon that he
had missed by staying so long with Basil hallwood Had he gone to his aunts he
would have been sure to have met Lord Goodbody there, and the whole
conversation would have been about the feeding of the poor and the necessity for model lodging
houses Each class would have preached the importance of those virtues, for
whose exercise there was no necessity in their own lives. The rich would have
spoken on the value of thrift, and the idol grown eloquent over the dignity of
Labor It was charming to have escaped all that! As he thought of his aunt, an idea
seemed to strike him. He turned to hallwood and said, “My dear fellow, I have just
remembered.” “Remembered what, Harry?” “Where I heard the name of Dorian
Gray.” “Where was it?” asked forward with a slight frown. “Don’t look so angry, Basil. It was
at my aunt, Lady Agatha’s. She told me she had discovered
a wonderful young man who was going to help her in the East End, and that his
name was Dorian Gray I'm bound to state that she never told me he was
good-look Women have no appreciation of good looks; at least, good women have not.
She said that he was very earnest and had a beautiful nature. I at once
pictured to myself a cre creature with spectacles and lank hair, horribly
freckled, and tramping about on huge feet.
I wish I'd known it was your friend I'm
very glad you didn’t, Harry.” “Why?” “I don’t
want you to meet him.” “You don’t want me
to meet him?” “No.” “Mr. Dorian Gray is in the studio, sir,” said the butler, coming into
the garden. “You must introduce me now,” cried Lord Henry, laughing. The painter
turned to his servant, who stood blinking in the sunlight.
“Ask Mr. Gray to wait, Parker: I shall be in
in a few moments.” The man bowed and went up the
walk. Then he looked at Lord Henry. “Dorian Gray is my dearest friend,” he said. “He has
a simple and a beautiful nature. Your aunt was quite right in what she said of
him. Don’t spoil him. Don’t try to influence him. Your influence would be
bad. The world is wide, and has many marvelous people in it. Don’t take away
from me the one person who gives to my art whatever charm it possesses: my life
as an artist depends on him. Mind, Harry, I trust you.” He spoke very slowly, and the
words seemed rung out of him almost against his will. “What nonsense you talk!”
said Lord Henry, smiling, and taking hwood by the arm, he almost led him into the
house D to chapter